Hi.
So if I ask you to give me the explanation
of how do you go about monitoring the
health of your system, you'll probably
come up with a pretty exhaustive and
long answer about the methodology
and the tools that you are using.
But if I ask you how you are making
sure that your team is doing okay, your
ans-answer might fall pretty short.
That's what this talk is about.
Today, I will share with you a methodology
to ensure that your engineers are
doing well, and more specifically,
focusing on incident responders.
At the end of this talk, you will
understand what the impact of being
on call for your engineers what's
happening in the AI era, what's the
impact, what are the things that you
can look at, the the process that you
can put in place to ensure that you
keep tab of what's happening, and a
few user stories, success stories from
companies who adopted this methodology.
So according to a recent survey
by Catchpoint, most software
engineer are on call, and being
on call can be rough for us.
It can cause stress, which can
ultimately negatively impact people's
ability to do their job and, really
also get in the way of life and
more specifically personal life.
The same survey found that the vast
majority of engineers experience some,
some sort of stress during incidents.
Maybe surprising is that also
the vast majority of engineer are
stressed after an incident is over.
And while they didn't go into the
why, my assumption is that a lot of
time, solving the incident is just the
first part of the, the entire process.
Then you may have to document what
happened, which can take a lot of
time, might have to do a lot of
paperwork, and the follow-up work can
be, quite important to create the task
and then actually work on the tasks.
And so engineers might be
stressed with that because
it's generally is not fun work.
Another reason is that while blameless
culture has been around for a while,
there's still a lot of companies that are
not really adopting that, and so engineer
might be blamed for, their inability, if
I may say, to solve the incident faster.
Finally, another stat that really
caught my eyes is the fact that more
than half of respondents reported
that their sleep was being impacted
where when they were on call, even if
they were not getting paged, right?
So the simple fact that you know you
are on call and you can be woken up or
called at any time is staying in the
pa-back of your brain and, impacts you.
I could not find that data specifically
for incident responders, but I did-
Found data for doctors who are on
call for a long period of time.
A study found that they were
five times more likely to commit
serious diagnostic errors because
of the impact of being on call.
Now, that's the current state.
Obviously, in the last few years, the
way that we've been building, shipping,
and maintaining software has been
drastically changing because of GenAI.
And so I wanted to briefly go
over that and see what's the
impact for incident responders.
Before I get into that, I just
wanted to briefly introduce me.
My name is Sylvain.
I lead the AI labs at Rootly.
Rootly is an incident
management and on-call platform.
We also provide an AI series that helps
our customers solve their incident
as well and as fast as possible.
My role at the AI lab is to explore
what AI, more specifically LLMs, can
bring to the world of reliability.
Everything we do at the
labs is open source.
We build prototypes, tools.
We do a lot of research that
we share with the community.
And when I'm not helping companies
solve their incidents, I'm helping
bees manage their incidents, and
turns out they have a lot of them.
I wanted to anchor, anchor this
talk into the incident rate formula.
What's really important in this
formula is the C and the P. C is the
number of changes brought to a system
in a given amount of time, and P is
the probability that one of these
changes is introducing a failure.
As C is drastically increasing nowadays,
and so there is a chance that your
number of incident might look like that.
Obviously, this is an artist's
representation, not the actual number.
But because I work for an
incident management company, I
decided to look at the numbers.
I looked at the average number
of incidents for U-- Rootly users
since twenty twenty-three, which is
when GenAI was emerging, and since
then it has increased by three.
Now, correlation is not causation, but
there is a lot of signal that points
to GenAI being, the cause of this.
One notable one was that a few months
ago, Amazon held an all-hands for
their engineering organization.
They were having too many outages, and
they wanted to do something about it,
and GenAI was pointed as one of the
main cause of this increase in outages.
Another impact of GenAI for
incident responders is that
developer are losing familiarity,
losing touch with their code base.
As an incident responder, if there is
an outage that is tricky you cannot
solve, you would look at the team or
the individual in charge of the service
or, you know, feature or whatnot,
go to them and ask them for help.
The answer you may get now is, "Hey,
sorry, mate, I didn't really write
this piece of code. I prompted my agent
to do it. I cannot really help you."
The other impact is that engineer are
increasingly asked to be, full stack or
be more, have an impact on a wider scope.
And so the number of
domain expert is lowering.
Let's say you need someone with very
sharp, let's say, I don't know, on
the MySQL database or whatnot, because
this outage is specifically about this.
Incident responder may have a harder
time to find this, this type of help.
And so the summary of the last few
slides is that incident responder
might have to handle more incidents
while getting less help while their
man- their manager is like chop.
You need to do more with less because
you have AI by your side." So it can
be quite a bit of a tricky situation.
So what can you do about it?
Obviously, there is a
ton of answers to that.
Today, I want to specifically
focus on the human aspect.
This conference is about monitoring.
I wanted to share with you, this
monitoring for human, and I want
to open this part of the talk
with a post from my friend Chris
could not have done it better.
He shared that the standard for our
industry is to measure the health of
our software, but to stand out is to
measure the health o- of your humans.
And so we've worked on this at the AI Labs
at Rootly, and we found that there are two
types of metric that you should look at.
These two types are observed
data and self-reported data.
I'm gonna go into explaining each of them.
So for observed data, I would
say it's pretty straightforward.
It's things like how many shifts did
an, an individual or a team handled?
How many incident and
pages did they respond to?
What was the severity of this incident?
Were they working during
weekend and at night?
All of this will basically
tell you how much work a team
or individual is handling.
But recently, we also found a, a new
trend where, you should look at the number
of tokens used by a team or individual
and so when they are u- using it.
Axios actually recently wrote about this.
They found that a number of engineers
and founder were sharing distress because
they were token maxing constantly.
YC CEO shared on Twitter that, he was
getting in this state of psychosis
where he would stay up for twenty,
twenty hours at a time, could not
sleep un- until five or six AM.
Our CTO, Quentin Rousseau, was in a
similar situation Could not sleep for
months was addicted to agentic coding.
Had to go to a doctor who
prescribed him sleeping pills.
There is more and more people sharing
this experience on the internet, and
so you should really look at token
consumption for your developer.
Company used to l- used to make sure
that developer use a lot, which can be
a good thing if they are properly used.
But yeah, if you see an engineer token
maxing and also at night, maybe they
automated their work and it's good,
but maybe they need help and you need
to have a conversation with them.
The second type of data that you should
collect is self-reported data, right?
And you can do this with two simple
question How are you feeling today?
And what's having the
biggest impact on you?
That can be done in person during
a one-on-one, or that can be
done through Slack or survey.
I recommend doing both because sometime
people might not be comfortable doing
it in person or online or vice versa.
And so offering both
offer more possibilities.
And so these two questions are actually
inspired from a framework that is used
in the clinical world called the EMA.
For instance, Apple is using it with
the Apple Health on on the watch.
So yeah if you're interested, you
can read more about the methodology.
All right, now you have this data,
then what do you do with it, right?
How do you interpret it?
We found that there are two main
ways to compute leverages data.
The first one is to create a risk level.
It can be on a scale to, ten or 100.
Here I picked 100, and it's
basically a compound of all this
signal that we, we collected, right?
But you need to be careful with the score
and make sure that it's put into context
and that you don't compare individual
teams or even, let's say, companies,
because the context matters a lot, right?
The way teams might work might be very
different, how they organize their
work and so on and so forth, or the
mon- their monitoring or what, let's
say, save zero or save one, right?
There's so many criterias that you really
need to look at the score in isolation.
Let me give you an example,
very concrete example.
Let's say you have a team of four SREs,
and you see the score at Mary being at
eighty, and you're like, "Wow, that's
quite high." But Mary has fifteen
years of experience being on call.
Save zero is a piece of cake.
She's done this so many times
that, for her it's no problem.
While on the other side, you might
have Bob, w- who has a score of
twenty-five, but he just recently
started in the industry, and so just to
save zero for him is very overwhelming.
And so a score of twenty-five is
actually not okay for him, right?
So yeah, risk level is the
first thing to look at.
The second one is perhaps more
importantly is the trend, right?
So you should look at how the
risk level of your teams and
individual is evolving over time.
This risk is drastically increasing
in a short amount of time or even
On a maybe not short amount of time,
but a longer, and it's like creeping
and you don't really see, right?
That, that can mean that the
situation is not going in the right
direction, and you need to step in.
So yeah, one good way to approach
if you want to put this framework
in place, is to make sure that the
risk level for each of your team and
individual is at the right level, and
then make sure that it's not growing.
Now, none of this, these
signals are diagnostic.
We are not medical experts, but
It's a conversation starter, right?
Worst case scenario, it's a false
positive, and you checked in on your
team, and you made sure everything
is all right, and everything is
all right, and it's good, right?
And maybe that will help you to find
something you didn't see, right?
Especially if you have a large
team or there is people working
remotely, it can be very hard
to keep tab on what's happening.
So always take the number with a
grain of salt, but it gives you
a rough idea and trend on what's
happening, and this has a lot of value.
So you can implement all of this yourself
and, especially now with GenAI it's
easy to build tools or you can use
a version that we built at the lab.
It's called OnCall Health.
It's free open source
under Apache license.
We are offering an hosted version.
You can also self-host it.
You can plug it into your
favorite incident management
tool like Rootly, PagerDuty.
We support Datadog, Linear, Jira,
Slack, and so on and so forth.
It's very exhaustive list of integration.
Everything that I shared in this talk,
pretty much we do it and even we have
other feature and way to interpret
the data that I didn't explain.
But yeah, feel free to check it out.
Before finishing this talk, I wanted
to share with you two user stories
while using the OnCall Health
methodology and share h-how they
used it and what was the benefit.
The first story I want to share is the
story of Casey Brown, who had recently
started a new job as the head of
infras-infrastructure engineering at
Weights & Biases, which is a company
that was recently acquired by CoreWeave.
As a good leader would do, he went
to his teams and spoke to everyone
to, to, understand how they were
doing, what were the challenges, and
on-call came up quite a bit, right?
Lot of people complained about
it, but Casey was not sure
exactly what was going on.
It was not too clear.
So he asked an engineer to
start trying to collect data.
The engineer was not too sure
how to approach this request.
And at the same time they discovered
us, and so they were able to put the
tool in place, collect some data.
Casey had a lot of ideas and assumption
on how they could improve the on-call
situation, but he wanted to make sure
that this change, this would actually
move, the needle in the right direction.
So OnCall Health allowed them to have
a before and after, which, ensured
that their engineer were happy.
The second story is with Joshua Inoa,
who is an engineering manager at Brex.
Every week, engineering leaders gather
to discuss the state of incidents and
one manager week has to report on the
health of their incident responders.
Historically, that was something that was
taking a lot of times for this engineering
manager to prepare and was anecdotal.
So what they like by using OnCall
Health is now it's data backed, right?
And, it makes the work way much faster
and make sure they don't have any coworker
burning out and they, do everything
they can to retain their best talent.
That's it.
That's the end of the talk.
I'm very active on LinkedIn.
If you want to connect with
me, I put it a QR code here.
If you are interested in trying
OnCall Health, try the hosted version.
If you log in, there is mock data,
so you can get a feel for the tool or
building yourself, as I shared earlier.
And if there is one thing that you
should remember from this talk, is
that you should start measuring.
Thank you for listening.